Guide to the William Martin Religious Right research collection, 1975-2000 MS 537
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
- Series II: Subject files, 1978-1996 (Boxes 77-91)
  - Subseries A: Alphabetical subject files
    - Fringe (Box 80, Folder 4)
      - The Salt and the Light (Box 80, Folder 4, Subfolder 1)
        The Salt and The Light a publisher of Christian organizations including newspaper of the Christian Political Party, and a scan of a book entitled the "National Sunday Law" by Jan Marcussen from 1995.
      - The Fringe: Militias (Box 80, Folder 4, Subfolder 2)
        This folder includes original news article from the New York Times, 1995, about E Pluribus Unum and other "Patriot Groups" and scans about Timothy McVeigh. There was also an article by Charles Coulson.
      - Fringe - literature (Box 80, Folder 4, Subfolder 3)
        This folder includes the "Field Manual Section 1: Principles Justifying the Arming and Organizing of a Militia" from 1994, which explains how and why one can and should set up a paramilitary Christian organization in America. There were also pamphlets about the growth of Fringe organizations. In addition, there was a Anti-Focus of the Family and Conservative Canadian magazine Briarpatch from 1992-1994. Sample of a selection of primary and secondary sources entitled "Far Right Theocrats and Anti-Choice Organizing published by the Political Research Associates."
    - Georgia (Box 80, Folder 5)
      Grassroots Christian Coalition organization in Georgia.
      - Cobb County (Box 80, Folder 5, Subfolder 1)
        Folder includes a July 1995 article from the magazine Glamour about LGBT life and prejudice in Cobb County Georgia.
    - Georgia Christian Coalition (Box 80, Folder 6)
      Folder includes articles from the Atlanta Journal and Constitution from 1989 and 1992 about the politics of the Conservative Coalition in GA. There was also a scan of newsletter from Family News in Focus Auguest 26, 1992.
    - Gingrich, Newt (Box 80, Folder 7)
      This includes scanned news articles from the New York Times, Business Weekly, and a poem entitled "the Gingrich Who Stole Congress," along with a scanned biography of Newt Gingrich, a scanned list of his reps, and newspaper from the New York Times.
    - Goldwater (Box 80, Folder 8)
      There is an annotated transcript of Goldwater's Republican National Convention acceptance speech in early 1964, typed and handwritten notes on Goldwater and his 1964 campaign, a chapter from a book entitled "Portraits of Two Women" another 2 sections from "The Republican Party 1854-1966," one from "Fire in the Streets: America in the 1960s," one from "What happened to Goldwater?," a chapter by Barry Goldwater "A Conservative's Creed," and finally one from "The Goldwater Coalition."
    - Graham, Billy (Box 80, Folder 9)
      - Audio Transcripts (Box 80, Folder 9, Subfolder 1)
        Transcript from Graham on Larry King, and Graham audio tapes with summaries 005-019-2.
      - Billy Graham (Box 80, Folder 9, Subfolder 2)
        This folder includes a scanned book review of the book "The Billy Graham Story," a story from the New York Times with some annotations, and a scanned chapter of "America's Sensational Young Evangelist (1918-1949)," along with an original 1993 November Time magazine cover story about Billy Graham, and finally handwritten notes from A Prophet with Honor.
      - Billy Graham Archives (Box 80, Folder 9, Subfolder 3)
        This folder includes a list of video tapes held by the Archive of the Billy Graham Center, a video tape list, a index and chronology of Goldwater video tapes, location records and a video tapes.
    - Gray, Nellie (Box 80, Folder 10)
      Folder was about Gray, a leader for the "March for Life" and scanned news articles from the New York Times in 1981.
    - Ground Zero (Box 80, Folder 11)
      Folder includes Ground Zero News original newsletters from 1994-1995. This newsletter dedicated to exploring issues of importance for the GLBT Communities. The newsletter is distributed from Colorado Springs.
    - Hargis (Box 80, Folder 12)
      Folder includes a scanned biography of Hargis a major Christian preacher in the 1950s, along with a chronography, a scanned chapter entitled "The American Far Right: A Case Study of Billy James Hargis and Christian Crusade." Also there were 4 christian crusade newsletters from 1995, scanned news articles "America's Other Radicals" chapter 1970, and Saturday Evening Post in 1962. Hargis' Favorite Hymns (official Christian Crusade song book), Hargis chronology, and Christian Crusade v. IRS published from Christian Crusade.
    - Hate Crimes (Box 80, Folder 13)
      Folder includes news articles about Doug Wead, a 700 Club newsletter from November 1990, and various news transcripts.
    - Hatfield, Mark (Box 80, Folder 14)
      Folder includes annotated forward that Hatfield, a longtime US Senator from Oregon, wrote against the Religious Right. Also includes a review of Hatfield's book "Conflict and Conscience," an anti-religious right book and a number of farther-right primary challengers. There are some handwritten notes and summary of Hatfield's views, scans of other chapters of his work, and transcripts of his speeches from the 1970s to the 1990s, especially from the mid 1970s.
    - Heritage Foundation (Box 80, Folder 15)
      Folder includes a pamphlet from the Heritage foundation sub-group Empower America, and the Heritage Foundations Policy Review from Fall 1990, and other scanned pamphlets There is also a newsletter from the Traditional Values Coalition, "The Index of Leading Cultural Indicators" March 1993, and "School Choice Programs" 1993, along with a National Empowerment Television folder.
    - Hill, E.V. (Box 80, Folder 16)
      An African American evangelical preacher who aligned himself with Billy Graham. Annotated story on Dr. Hill and his job as a preacher in Pasadena CA, and a story entitled "Maintaining the Momentum"
    - Homosexuality (Box 80, Folder 17)
      This folder includes newspaper about homosexuality in the Republican Party, along with a number of scans of news articles and of The Advocate, 1993, about Christianity and LGBT, original news article about Florida, and a Ground Zero News Newsletter. There was scanned newspaper about Colorado Anti-LGBT sentiment, transcript from CNN, scanned book review of "Stonewall," Family Defense Council Newsletter, and Traditional Values Coalition. There were articles about support for anti-LGBT coalition, multiple other original newspaper articles about LGBT members in the military, gay rights cases, and homesexuality in advertisments.
    - Institute for First Amendment Studies (Box 80, Folder 18)
      Folder includes Freedom Writer monthly newsletters from 1992-1995 which are against the religious right, fighting for the separation of Church and State, and pamphlets from the Institute For First Amendment Studies. Institue was a major critic of the Christian Right and Religious Right and photos of members of the Institute.
    - Institute for Government Studies (Box 80, Folder 19)
      Folder includes 1995 book catalog from UC Berkeley, and a list of working papers and authors from 1987-1995.
    - Jepsen, Dee (Box 80, Folder 20)
      Folder includes scanned newspaper articles from 1983-1985. Jepsen worked for the Reagan administration. Also included Woman of the New Right, a biography of Jepsen from the 1990s about her presidency of "Enough is Enough," and resume.
    - JFK Info (Box 80, Folder 21)
      - JFK Info (Box 80, Folder 21, Subfolder 1)
        A selection of scanned newspaper articles from 1960 about Kennedy's Catholicism, articles from Awake The Catholic Church in the 20th Century, some political cartoons, and anti-Catholic propaganda. There was also archival series and folder titles from the Kennedy campaign, JFK, and evangelicals, handwritten notes.
      - JFK - Space/Religion (Box 80, Folder 21, Subfolder 2)
        Folder includes transcript of Kennedy speech at Rice University, JFK Library audio visual reproduction service, scanned Radio and Television remarks of Kennedy all with some annotations.
    - Journal Graphics (Box 80, Folder 22)
      Folder includes interview with George Gallup, polling of Americans spiritual values. Journal Graphics topic alert service report about their transcripts. Used this service to get transcripts for the religious right documentary with transcript requests. Transcript from Gallup, from CNN about the Gay Rights Campaign in Cobb County and Bill Moyers' Journal (PBS) transcripts, handwritten notes.
    - Julie Lewis/ Joyce Claypool (Box 80, Folder 23)
      Folder includes scanned and original article from August 1995 about the loss of Kara Claypool-a young girl with AIDS.
    - Kanawha County (Box 80, Folder 24)
      - Kanawha County (Box 80, Folder 24, Subfolder 1)
        Folder includes chapter of a book "Tales out of School," and an article "The Kanawha County Textbook Controversy," a chapter on "The Textbook War in Kanawha County." Also, Interview tape from the documentary With God on Our Side. Handwritten notes, articles about organizations and individuals opposed to Sex Education. Handwritten and typed notes about Kanawha and its use in the documentary.
      - Kanawha - Sex Ed (Box 80, Folder 24, Subfolder 2)
        Folder includes book chapter in "Storm in the Mountains" with annotations about sexual education in the West Virginian Kanawha County.
      - Kanawha Religious Right (Box 80, Folder 24, Subfolder 3)
        Folder included scanned encyclopedia pages about the educational controversy in West Virginia some highlighting, scanned news articles, and highlights of the scanned NY Times 1975 Index, about the textbook battle scanned.
      - Press: Kanawha County (Box 80, Folder 24, Subfolder 4)
        Folder includes another scanned textbook battle articles, essays about censorship, Kanawha timeline and news coverage, and a summary of Kanawha treatment in 1995. Also, lists of involved people, handwritten notes on the publicity and coverage. Also, guide to the literature from West Virginia, news transcripts and highlighted articles.
      - Kanawha Treatments (Box 80, Folder 24, Subfolder 5)
        Folder includes summary or intro to a book or article entitled "Kanawha: The Battle of the Books."
      - Kanawha Correspondence (Box 80, Folder 24, Subfolder 6)
        Folder includes correspondence between the production company of "With God on our Side" and members of textbook controversy, which will be a major part of the series.
    - Kilberg, Bobbie G. (Box 80, Folder 25)
      Folder includes resume of Bobbie Greene Kilberg who worked in the George H. W. Bush administration as its Deputy Assistant to the President for Public Liaison.
    - Koop, C. Everett (Box 80, Folder 26)
      Immediate Source of Acquisition
      Folder includes scanned New York Times articles about Koop, the AIDS crisis, how he angered the religious right, and changing sex education. Also included Koop timeline, a chapter of a book entitled "President Reagan: The Role of a Lifetime," edition of the Moody Monthly from May 1980, and scanned articles from the Washington Times, New York Times, and Washington Post etc. Reports on AIDS, Koop's calls for comprehensive sex education, Family Protection Report, and address by Koop of US Public Health Service to the National Religious Broadcasters from February 2, 1987, and a large number of scanned articles. A statement by Koop before the Committee on Energy and Commerce in the House about AIDS, from the mid to late 80s, and a Religion and Society Report.
    - Kuhlman, Kathryn (Box 80, Folder 27)
      Folder includes a biography from 1974 of Kuhlman, a Protestant minister and faith healer born in 1946.
    - LaHaye (Box 80, Folder 28)
      - Concerned Women of America (Box 80, Folder 28, Subfolder 1)
        Folder includes a memo of the materials from the Texas Concerned Women of America conference from February 1989. Book reviews of Kay Coles James book "Transforming America from the Inside Out."
      - Tim & Beverly LaHaye (Box 80, Folder 28, Subfolder 2)
        The folder about the LaHaye's are conservative christian authors and speakers. Includes some mass mail from LaHaye, a biography of Tim and Beverly LaHaye (3 copies), an article from Mother Jones, and handwritten notes and report about Lake County.
    - Law and Justice Journal (Box 80, Folder 29)
      Folder includes a copy of Law and Justice Journals from 1993 and pamphlets by Keith A. Fournier. Along with a copy from Human Events (The National Conservative Weekly) original from 1993, World, American Center for Law and Justice Chief Counsel's Report. This organization was run by Pat Robertson.
    - Left Becoming Right (Box 80, Folder 30)
      Folder includes scans from newspaper or journal "Did the Right Hijack Civil Rights Group? Meyers' Foes Say Yes," article "Going to Extremes" by Philip Weiss about the pastor Richard Neuhaus converts from Sixties radical to Eighties Reaganite.
    - Leftist Lit (Box 80, Folder 31)
      Folder includes National Coalition Against Censorship newsletter from 1994 and Human rights campaign fund pamphlet and newsletters, and a letter from the Democratic Socialists of America about the 1994 election.
    - Legal Cases (Box 80, Folder 32)
      - Brittany Settle (Box 80, Folder 32, Subfolder 1)
        Folder includes scanned news article from New York Times from 1995 when the Supreme Court turned down a case about Christianity and schools.
      - Legal Cases (Box 80, Folder 32, Subfolder 2)
        Folder includes original newspaper article about the Scopes Trial and an article in Opposition Research entitled "See Them in Court: The Christian Right Makes Use of the Court System" and a scan of an Associated Press article.
    - Legislation (Box 80, Folder 33)
      Folder includes an email from John Lewis, some Case Notes from The Civil Rights Restoration Act of 1987—A Defeat for Judicial Conservatism, and Effects of the 1987 Civil Rights Restoration Act on Educational Policy and Practice. Finally there was also Congressional Quarterly 100th and 101st sessions and CRS Reports for Congress on Hate Crime and Hate Violence.
    - McIntire, Carl (Box 80, Folder 34)
      Folder includes scans of newspaper articles about the Reverend Carl McIntire and his shock radio show, preaching from outside of US airwaves, 1980s.
    - Mawyer, Martin (Box 80, Folder 35)
      Folder includes articles by members of the Christian Action Network, such as one about LGBT members of the military, and an article entitled Sex Greed Power. Also, how Christian Citizen's affect political change, Christian Action Network timeline and interview questions, annotated and highlighted newspapers, and poll questions about LGBT rights.
    - Media (Box 81, Folder 1)
      - Media: Political Media (Box 81, Folder 1, Subfolder 1)
        Folder includes scanned and annotated New York Times along with New York Times originals from the early to mid-nineties, and scanned articles from World News.
      - Right-Wing Media (Box 81, Folder 1, Subfolder 2)
        Folder has a quarterly newsletter from the National Empowerment Television, a right-wing television network, from the summer of 1993.
      - Media: Critical of Secular Media (Box 81, Folder 1, Subfolder 3)
        Folder includes original newspaper from the New York Times, such as a 1993 book review of "The Culture of Disbelief." and other scans and original newspapers. Also information from the Media Research Center, a conservative media research group, and newsletters from "The Report" and the "Media Research Center" about the entertainment industry from the early 1990s.
      - Christian Media (Box 81, Folder 1, Subfolder 4)
        Folder includes packet from August 1994 of The Catholic Communication Campaign, a request for media proposals form and lists of proposals from July 1994, 7 proposals and an article scan from Religious Broadcasting about Christian Film and Television Commission. Also included an article about the growing Christian Rock.
    - Media Coalition (Box 81, Folder 2)
      Folder includes a summary page of what the Media Coalition was and their 1992 highlights. Along with an annotated report from the Media Coalition about the Reverend Donald Wildmon's Crusade for Censorship from 1977-1992.
    - Metzger, Leigh Ann (Box 81, Folder 3)
      Folder includes scanned news articles about Metzger's role in the H.W. Bush administration as the liaison to Conservative religious groups, interview questions for Metzger, and notes about her interview.
    - Miscellaneous (Box 81, Folder 4)
      - Articles to be Filed (Box 81, Folder 4, Subfolder 1)
        Folder includes mix of scanned news articles, and news articles. Also, business deal with Avid Considerations, a chapter from Horton's "Beyond Culture Wars," a chapter about anti-Communist films entitled "A Broader Mind," and an article about Kemp with annotations.
      - Misc. (Box 81, Folder 4, Subfolder 2)
        Folder includes original newspaper and scanned articles/chapters. An article about Intellectual Conservatism, a book review of "Culture of Complaint," an article about New York Times Holocaust Denial, and a review of a Dinesh D'Souza book and other book reviews. Also includes political cartoon, scanned chapter of Writer Revelations, and a scan of New York Times articles in 1995, and scans of the Dictionary of Christianity in America, "Why the Religious Right is Wrong," chapter of "Left Center Right" and God and Jimmy Carter highlighted. Also, highlighted chapters of "Preachers of Paradox," "'Billy, You Stay Out of Politics,'" "Prophet with Honor," "Nixon Revived," Appendix B of Treatments and Sample Tape, chapter of "Vocabulary of Public LIfe," scanned Wall Street Journal articles, and a chapter of "Exiles No Longer," chapter of "The Failure of the Religious Right."
      - General - Christian Right (Box 81, Folder 4, Subfolder 3)
        Folder includes 1993 New York Times Magazine article about the Christian Coalition's educated faithful, a collection of timelines, and a document with religious right resources from the internet. A chapter on Chronology religious broadcasting, and transcripts of New York Times articles, a Time magazine on Ralph Reed and politics of sin article. Also includes other scanned news articles, second coming, evangelical voters polling data.
      - General Ep. 6 Searches (Box 81, Folder 4, Subfolder 4)
        Folder included scanned news article about Lynchburg VA,and a transcript of news from Cobb County GA.
    - Rise of Moral Majority (Box 81, Folder 5)
      - Falwell & Abortion & Moral Majority (Box 81, Folder 5, Subfolder 1)
        Folder includes a transcript of news articles from 1984-1993 with highlights, scans about the Moral Majority from 1981 and transcript of news articles about Moral Majority. The folder also includes a chapter titled "To Rule and Reign" and another entitled "If I Should Die Before I Wake: Jerry Falwell's Pro-Life Gospel," and a Carter administration era Moral Majority Report Card from 1980. Finally the folder has a transcript of a 1982 interview of Falwell, and a Connecticut mutual life report.
      - Cal Thomas (Box 81, Folder 5, Subfolder 2)
        Folder includes biographical information about the Moral Majority's vice president for communications, scanned news articles from the New York Times, Christian Today, and Lynchburg news.
      - Moral Majority Report, 1980-1982 (Box 81, Folder 5, Subfolder 3)
        Folder includes scanned articles and information from the Moral Majority Report Card in 1980-1982, information about the Carter white house competing against the Moral Majority, and an educational tax credit for private school parents.
      - Ed Dobson (Box 81, Folder 5, Subfolder 4)
        Folder includes a Brick in Architecture article about the Calvary Church addition in July, 1994.
      - Founding of Moral Majority & Rise (Box 81, Folder 5, Subfolder 5)
        Folder includes 1979-1982 news article transcripts and Heritage Foundation Policy Reviews. 1980 Newsweek about "Born-Again Politics," and a Falwell Press Conference from 1987 transcript announcing his pull-back from politics.
    - Morken, Hubert (Box 81, Folder 6)
      Folder includes biographical information of Morken, a professor of Government at Regent University, along with a Resume of Morken, and a thesis or book by Morken entitled "The San Diego Model: Religious-Identity Concealment as Political Strategy" from 1993. Also has scanned newsletters, and another thesis or book "The Evangelical Legal Response to the ACLU: Religion, Politics, and the First Amendment" published in 1992. Finally a newsletter, "'No Special Rights': The Thinking Behind Colorado's Amendment #2 Strategy," and another entitled "Religious Lobbying at the State Level: Case Studies in a Continuing Role for the New Religious Right."
    - Moyers Transcripts (Box 81, Folder 7)
      Folder includes transcript from a panel with Moyers about his Anti-ACLU feelings. Also includes four pamphlets and transcripts of Bill Moyers TV appearances from 1987-1992.
    - Music (Box 81, Folder 8)
      - Music - Religious Memos & Articles (Box 81, Folder 8, Subfolder 1)
        Folder includes a Manhattan record shop list, timelines of Contemporary Christian music, and music of "With God On Our Side by Bob Dylan. Also includes emails and faxes from and to Lumiere Productions, handwritten letters, and an article from the Journal of Popular Culture "Contemporary Christian Music: Where Rock Meets Religion." Finally, a Cassette master listening list, and a newsletter entitled "Lighting Candles" from 1995.
      - Contemporary Christian Music (Box 81, Folder 8, Subfolder 2)
        Folder includes Contemporary Christian Music magazine article from June 1995, a Gospel Music summary, and scanned newspaper articles. Also an article from the Journal of Popular Culture "Contemporary Christian Music: Where Rock Meets Religion," highlighted, and a folder from the Christian rock band Gaithers.
      - Religious Right Music (Box 81, Folder 8, Subfolder 3)
        Folder includes new Pinebrook Songs booklet from the "Young People's Church of the Air" from 1939.
    - National Campaign for Freedom of Expression (Box 81, Folder 9)
      National Campaign for Freedom of Expression (NCFE) Winter 1994 Bulletin, art, and membership newsletter and NCFE Summer 1993 bulletin.
    - NEA and NEH (Box 81, Folder 10)
      Folder includes a newspaper about Keely and Du play, a budget form from the National Endownment of the Humanities, and a newsletter from anti-National Endownment of the Arts from the American Family Association, from the early 1990s. Also includes, original articles from The Nation about state of the arts in Cobb County, and an article and scan of Sharon Percy Rockefeller.
    - Foundation for New Era of Philanthropy (Box 81, Folder 11)
      Folder includes four newspaper article scans from 1995 about the financing of the charity named the Foundation for New Era Philanthropy.
    - New Right (Box 81, Folder 12)
      Folder includes a summary of figures in the New Right including Jerry Falwell, Phyllis Schafly, and scans of articles entitled "The New Christian Right" from 1985, "The Appeal of The New Right" from 1984, "The New Right" by Moser, and"Who's Who in the Conservative Establishment."
    - Newman, Ann (Box 81, Folder 13)
      Folder includes Texas Family Research Center newsletters and memos, scanned news articles from San Antonio in 1995, and a report from Anne Newman from March 1994, entitled "High School Health Textbooks: Hazardous to Your Children's Health." Finally another report from Anne Newman entitled "The Sex Pushers: Your Children the Target" form 1992.
    - Nixon (Box 81, Folder 14)